RESTAURANT HANASAKI
（花琦居酒屋）
These are souvenirs for you guys.
有伴手礼哦
How nice!
那怎么好意思？
Thanks.
谢谢
Local sake, a lucky charm and a phone strap for Dad.
给爸爸的是当地的清酒、护身符 还有一条手机吊饰
A power stone bracelet and rice cakes for Mr. Soma.
给相马的是灵石手串和点心
Shrine tour with girlfriends on a summer vacation?
难得的暑假竟然跟女性朋友游神社
I'd rather get a souvenir from your honeymoon.
我情愿等你新婚旅行才送我礼物呢
Come on, Dad.
真不识货啊 爸
This Enishi Shrine is a popular power spot right now.
这座缘师神社 可是当下热门的风水宝地呢
After a three-day visit, I am fully charged.
拜访三天之后 我已经充满电了
Power spot?
风水宝地啊？
Walking around this sacred tree will grant your wish.
据说 绕着这棵神树走一圈 就能实现一个愿望
I did it three times.
我都绕了三圈了
What did you wish for?
那你许了什么愿望？
I'm not telling you.
我才不告诉你们呢
Not that I care to know.
反正我也不是很想听
If I remember correctly, Enishi Shrine is famous for matchmaking, right?
我没记错的话 这座缘师神社 是以求姻缘闻名的地方吧？
Really?
真的吗？
I see.
原来如此
My friend really wanted to go.
是我朋友亚纪想去的啦
Don't worry. I understand that there are times when you need God's help.
别紧张 总会有想要求神的时候嘛
I am not desperate like you, Mr. Soma.
我又没有相马你那么着急
I'm not desperate.
我可不着急哦
Mai. This lucky charm is for love and romance.
小舞 这是保佑恋爱顺利的护身符呢
I thought it was for business.
不是保佑生意兴隆的吗？
-It's okay. I'll keep it. -Sorry.
-没关系 我就拿着吧 -抱歉
After all, I'm single too.
毕竟我也是单身嘛
Dad will get all the benefits from the sacred tree.
那你绕的那三圈 就会应验到你爸身上了
-That'll be nice. -Come on.
-那还不错呢 -拜托啦
KAWASAKI BRANCH
（川崎分行）
Get that contract with Sumikura Shoji.
记得把住仓贸易的合约处理好
Leave it to us.
交给我们吧
Branch Manager, we'll be off.
那我们先走了 水原经理
-Okay. -Good night.
-好的 -告辞
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK
（东京第一银行）
We're in trouble…
大事不好了
What's wrong, Mr. Shibasaki?
怎么了 芝崎次长？
Did they find something odd during your check-up?
是你体检的结果不好吗？
No.
不是啦
Kawasaki's Branch Manager was attacked.
川崎分行的分行经理被人袭击了
Attacked?
-被袭击了？
Someone shoved him off the stairs on his way home from the branch.
他昨晚离开分行后 在回家的路上被人推下楼梯了
And the culprit?
犯人呢？
He ran away.
当场逃跑了
The Branch Manager broke his leg and was hospitalized.
那个经理腿部骨折 现在住院中
That's scary.
好可怕啊
Was it a random attack?
是被随机袭击的吗？
I can't say that for sure.
这个还不确定呢
That Branch Manager has always been notorious for being domineering.
那个分行经理是出了名地独裁专制
He doesn't have a good reputation.
别人对他的评价都不太好
He might have…
说不定…
Incurred someone's hatred?
是遭人报复吗？
He filed a claim with the police.
他本人已经报了警
But we don't want him to make a big deal about this.
但银行可不希望他把事情闹大啊
We must avoid involving the police,
一定要避免涉及警方
or it will diminish the credibility of Tokyo Daiichi Bank.
不然就会损害东京第一银行的名誉 对吧？
You are right.
说得没错
So please run over to Kawasaki and assess the situation.
所以 麻烦你们马上去川崎分行 查清楚情况
Run over? It's in Kawasaki.
马上？那可是在川崎啊
Kawasaki!
川崎
That's nice. Let's go, Mr. Soma.
挺好的啊 走吧 相马
Why are you up for it?
你想干嘛？
Kawasaki Daishi is a famous shrine and it's also a popular power spot.
那里有著名的川崎大师啊 也是热门的风水宝地
Let's go pray at lunchtime.
趁着午休去拜拜吧
She's going for the wrong reasons.
她的意图不太对呢
What are you doing, Mr. Soma? Hurry!
你在干嘛呢 相马？快点啦
Good luck.
拜托你们了
Okay.
是
KAWASAKI HOSPITAL
（川崎综合医院）
Branch Manager Mizuhara has received many awards.
水原经理被表彰过很多次呢
He will come back to Headquarters in a few years.
过几年就会被调回本部了
He's successfully going up the corporate ladder.
可谓步步高升、平步青云呢
Ah, is he possibly in…
对了 他该不会是…
Yes. Shindo faction.
就是真藤派的
I pray that nothing will happen.
老天保佑 一定不要出什么事啊
What are you praying for?
你在拜什么呢？
All right! I can feel luck on my side.
很好 我感觉运气围绕着我呢
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK
（东京第一银行）
It's here.
是这里
What is this proposal document?
这份报告是怎么回事？
Do you think this will be approved?
你认为这种东西能通过吗？
You're so incompetent.
真没用
Do it again.
回去重做
I am sorry.
非常抱歉
I can't believe you're the head of Finance. And you!
你这样还当什么融资课课长？ 小笠原
Yes.
是
As the Deputy Manager, you should be training him!
身为副理 你应该好好指导他才是
I am sorry.
非常抱歉
-Um… -Who are you?
-不好意思 -你们是谁啊？
Excuse me.
抱歉打扰了
You must be Kawasaki's Branch Manager Mizuhara.
你是川崎分行的水原经理吧？
I am Soma from Branch Inspection at headquarters.
我是分行稽核班的相马
I am Hanasaki.
我是花琦
What do you need?
你们来干嘛？
I am sorry to hear about what happened to you.
你遭遇这样的事 真是万分不幸
Can we ask for more details about what happened?
我们想来问问这次事件的一些细节
There are no more details.
没什么细节
A man shoved me off the stairs all of a sudden.
就是有个男人突然把我推下了楼梯
I heard you filed a claim with the police.
我们听说你已经报了警
Of course. I won't stay quiet about this.
当然了 我怎么能忍气吞声？
But they just came for a brief moment and left right away.
但他们只是问了两句话就回去了
They didn't even try to investigate the case,
像我那么老实的居民被袭击了
even though an honest citizen got hurt.
他们也没有要好好调查的意思
Are you certain that you were shoved?
你确定是被人推下楼梯的吗？
What are you talking about?
你什么意思啊？
Do you think I just slipped?
你的意思是我自己滑倒的吗？
No. I just heard that there were no witnesses.
不是的 但是当时并没有目击证人
Stay quiet, Branch Inspection.
区区一个稽核员 竟敢那么无礼
All you have to do is solve tiny problems occurring at the branches.
你们只需要解决 分行内的一些小问题就可以了
With all due respect…
请恕我直言…
Do you have any ideas about who it might be?
你有没有在怀疑的人呢？
Of course not.
当然没有了
Either way, this doesn't concern you.
反正这不关你们的事
Just leave.
快走吧
I understand. Thank you for your time.
知道了 那我们告辞了
Keep an eye on our staff and make sure they don't slack off while I'm away.
小笠原 我不在的时候 你要好好看着员工 别让他们偷懒
I will.
我知道了
They're good at slacking off.
他们可是很会偷懒的
-Do you understand? -Yes, I do.
-听明白了吗？ -明白了
What's wrong with that arrogant Branch Manager? He gets me so mad!
那个傲慢的经理是怎么回事？ 真令人火大啊
Hanasaki! Look back.
花琦 看后面
I am sorry.
不好意思
We are also sorry for causing such a scene in front of you.
我们才不好意思 让两位见笑了
I'm sure everyone working with him is having a hard time.
跟那样的人工作一定很辛苦吧？
Don't talk about unnecessary things.
别说多余的话
I heard that Mr. Mizuhara came to this post a year ago.
听说水原经理上任已经一年半了
Yes.
是的
Do you think he incurred someone's hatred during that time?
你们认为这段期间 他有与谁结过梁子吗？
As you saw earlier, he has a difficult personality. So he's had
如两位所见 他的性格就是那样难相处
trouble with many people.
所以结下的仇家也不少
He has had many problems concerning loans, too.
融资的纠纷也很多
You were with Mr. Mizuhara last night, until just before the incident.
昨晚直到案件发生之前 你们两位一直跟他待在一起
Did you see anything strange?
有发现什么异样吗？
I don't think so.
没什么特别的
I didn't notice anything either.
我也没发现什么
I see.
这样啊
May I see the list of customers that went bankrupt in the last year and a half?
我能不能看看过去一年半来 破产的企业资料？
Okay.
好的
-Mizuhara was hospitalized? -Yes.
-水原住院了？ -是的
Someone shoved him off the stairs on his way home.
有人在他回家的路上把他推下了楼梯
We live in dangerous times.
最近常常发生这样危险的事呢
They haven't made it clear whether it's a criminal case or not.
不过 目前还不确定是不是人为案件
That's all from me.
那我先出去了
He's always had lots of enemies.
那家伙从以前就树敌众多啊
Pardon?
你说什么？
No. Nothing.
没什么
It's true that he cuts off all companies that aren't performing well.
水原经理对于业绩不好的公司 就果断抛弃
It's understandable that these companies would hold a grudge against him.
如果这些公司对他心生怨恨 也是可以理解的
It all makes sense when you think about his personality.
你看他那个态度就知道了啊
He threw the proposal documents at his subordinates
居然将报告书扔到部下身上
and called them incompetent.
还说他们没用
I feel so sorry for the people who have to work under him.
我真的蛮同情 那些在他手下做事的人呢
I agree.
是啊
In that sense, I am so lucky to have you as my boss, Mr. Soma.
这样看来 我有你这样的上司真是太幸运了
You're sloppy and not ambitious,
因为你又马虎又没野心
and all I have to do is bear your cheesy jokes sometimes.
只需要偶尔忍受一下大叔的冷笑话
I have no complaints.
除此之外都不错啊
That's not a compliment.
这根本就不是夸奖
-Yes, it is. -How?
-我是在夸你啊 -哪有？
Anyway, we can't say for certain if Mr. Mizuhara was attacked or not.
总之 现在还不能断定 水原经理是不是被袭击的
Right.
没错
MUSASHIKOSUGI BRANCH
（武藏小杉分行）
BRANCH MANAGER RYOJI KANEDA
（分行经理 金田亮司）
Who is it?
是谁？
Good morning, Dad.
早啊 爸
Mai, your bank is in big trouble.
小舞 你们银行出大事了
What do you mean? You sound like Mr. Shibasaki.
出什么大事了？ 你的语气就像芝崎次长那样
A Branch Manager was attacked last night.
昨晚有位分行经理被袭击了
TWO BRANCH MANAGERS ATTACKED ONE AFTER THE OTHER
（东京第一银行 两名分行经理接连被袭击）
Musashikosugi Branch?
武藏小杉分行？
It says that he was hit by a pole.
说是被人用棍子突袭了
How scary.
真可怕
-This is Hanasaki. -Did you check the newspaper?
-我是花琦 -你看报纸了吗？
This can't be a coincidence.
这应该不是偶然吧？
It seems that they purposely attacked those two people.
看来犯人是有预谋地袭击了这两个人
Luckily, he wasn't seriously injured.
还好伤得并不严重
Hanasaki, let's go see Musashikosugi's Branch Manager.
花琦 我们去见见 那位武藏小杉分行经理吧
Okay.
好的
I was surprised because he attacked me all of a sudden.
那个人突然攻击我 吓了我一跳
I knew what had happened to Mr. Mizuhara,
我听说了水原经理的事
but I can't believe this.
只是没想到会发生在我身上
Do you have any idea about who the criminal might be?
请问你有关于犯人的线索吗？
None at all.
完全没有
I can't believe I was involved in such a thing.
没想到我竟然遇上这种事
Do you know Mr. Mizuhara from the Kawasaki branch?
请问你认识川崎分行的水原经理吗？
I worked with him at the Toranomon Branch eight years ago.
认识 我八年前 跟他在虎之门分行一起工作过
What were your job titles at the time?
你们两位当时的职位是…
Mr. Mizuhara was the Section Chief of Finance,
水原经理是融资课课长
and I was Deputy Manager.
而我是代理课长
Were there any problems with
那你在虎之门分行的时候
loans when you were at the Toranomon branch?
有遇过什么融资纠纷吗？
I don't remember.
我不记得了
There's always problems everywhere.
到处都有纠纷
There are countless numbers of customers who complain.
喜欢投诉的客户多不胜数
The two who were attacked had something in common.
这两个被袭击的人是有共同点的
Yes, they are both jerks.
对 两个都那么讨人厌
Stop it.
别说人是非
Toranomon Branch.
虎之门分行啊
Did they incur someone's hatred there?
应该是在那里被人记恨了吧？
It is possible.
应该是吧？
It could be that this case started at the Toranomon Branch.
这案子的源头说不定就是虎之门分行
Let's go.
走吧
This is Mizuhara.
我是水原
Branch Inspection just came to see me.
分行稽核班刚刚来看过我
They came to see me yesterday.
他们昨天也来找我了
Ignore them. They are useless.
别管他们 都是废物
Did you see the culprit's face?
你看到犯人的脸了吗？
No, it was too dark.
没看到 太暗了
It could be the same guy that attacked me.
可能跟袭击我的是同一个人
But… why did he attack us?
但他为什么要袭击我们呢？
How would I know?
我怎么知道？
Anyway, let me know if you find out anything about the culprit. Okay?
总之 如果你有任何犯人的线索 马上告诉我
Yes, I will.
好的
Now Kaneda was attacked?
金田也被袭击了吗？
Yes.
是的
It's troubling.
真是伤脑筋啊
Especially since you've been looking favorably upon those two.
毕竟那两位都是你你平时很关照的人
Please be careful, just in case.
为了慎重起见 你也要多加小心
Why do I have to be careful?
为什么我也要小心？
Just in case. I am sorry.
只是为了慎重起见 非常抱歉
TORANOMON BRANCH
（虎之门分行）
Unfortunately, I don't know much about what happened seven or eight years ago.
很遗憾 我不是很清楚七、八年前的事情
BRANCH MANAGER HISAYUKI HENMI
（分行经理 汴见久幸）
It hasn't been long since I came here.
我不久前才刚上任
I understand.
原来如此
I am sorry that I couldn't be of any help…
真抱歉 我帮不上什么忙
Well…
对了
There is a lady who has been working in the Finance Department since then.
融资课里有一个人 从那时开始一直工作到现在
She is an experienced member of the department.
她是资深的融资课事务员
I would like to see her.
请让我们见见她
I was so shocked.
我可是吓了一跳呢
After all, they were attacked in a row.
毕竟他两位是接连被袭击的
Everyone is talking about it.
大家都在讨论这件事呢
Can you tell us about those two bankers?
请问他们两位是怎样的人？
Let me see.
我想想啊
Mr. Mizuhara is the stereotypical alpha male.
水原先生是典型的老大
He spoiled those who he liked,
对自己喜欢的部下百依百顺
but he was super harsh on those who showed even a hint of defiance.
对稍微反抗他的人就超级苛刻
No wonder he has many enemies.
就是那样才会树敌过多吧？
-I see. -What about Mr. Kaneda?
-原来如此 -那金田经理呢？
He is Mr. Mizuhara's follower.
他是水原的手下
He's like a sidekick.
就是像跟班那样
He is a timid man who can't say no to his boss.
是个绝对服从老大命令的胆小鬼
I see.
这样啊
They are the kind of men you want to talk back to.
他们就是那种会让人想回嘴的人吧
Shut up.
闭嘴
Did they have any problems with the customers?
他们有和客人发生过纠纷吗？
I'm sure they had many problems.
纠纷可不少呢
But I think the biggest problem they had was…
不过 当中最严重的应该是那次吧？
Yes?
那次？
Wait a second.
请稍等一下
Here.
这个
OKAMURA STEEL
（冈村钢铁）
This is a file from seven years ago.
是七年前的资料啊
You still have this?
怎么还保存着？
The Branch Manager at that time was very strict.
当时的分行经理很严格
We have all the files saved here.
过去的资料都保存起来了
Okamura Steel?
冈村钢铁？
This company went bankrupt seven years ago.
这家公司是七年前破产的
The president came to the Finance Department and got violent.
那位社长还跑来我们融资课 大打出手呢
Violent?
大打出手？
He barged in and punched Mr. Mizuhara who was
他突然闯了进来
the Section Chief of the Finance Department.
对当时的融资课课长水原大打出手
It's all because of you.
都是因为你
We had to call the police and it was a big mess.
事情闹得很大 还惊动了警察呢
Why did he do that?
他为什么要打人呢？
I don't know much,
我也不太清楚
but people said that there was a problem before the bankruptcy.
有人说破产之前可能发生了什么事
Do you know how the President is doing now?
那位社长现在怎么样了？
I don't know.
我不知道
We have had no business with him since then.
在那之后 银行跟他就没有合作了
Oh no… Is President Okamura the one that attacked Mr. Mizuhara?
天啊 不会是冈村社长 袭击水原经理他们吧？
No. We don't know yet.
这个…我们还不确定
How scary.
真可怕啊
Is there anything else that you can think of?
还有什么其他的线索吗？
That's the only thing that left an impression on me.
我能想起来的就只有这么多了
There were lots of smaller problems, though.
不过 还有很多小小的纠纷啦
Okay. Thank you for your time.
好的 非常谢谢你的配合
It was very useful information.
你提供的资讯很有帮助
Really? That's good.
真的吗？那就好了
Excuse me.
我们先走了
Um…
那个…
Yes?
么什事？
I hope they catch the criminal soon.
没什么 要是能快点找到犯人就好了
Yes.
是啊
Mr. Mizuhara didn't mention anything about the physical attack.
水原经理都没提过被人打的事
We have to ask him again about Okamura Steel.
我们需要再问问他 冈村钢铁公司的事情呢
Do we have to see him again?
还要去找他吗？
I really don't like him.
真的不是很喜欢他呢
Don't say unnecessary things, whether you like him or not.
不管你喜不喜欢他 都不要乱说话
Whatever he says, just smile.
不管他说什么 你微笑就对了
I'll try.
我尽力吧
Okamura Steel?
冈村钢铁公司？
The police just asked me the same thing.
警方才刚问我一样的问题呢
The police?
警方？
It seems like they suspect Okamura.
他们好像在怀疑冈村
What do you think, Mr. Mizuhara?
那你是怎么想的呢？
If he's the culprit, then this is insane.
如果犯人是他的话 那可就太荒唐了
I heard you had a dispute with Okamura
听说你和冈村社长
at the Toranomon Branch over the bankruptcy issue.
因为公司破产的事 曾经有过纠纷呢
We heard that you were struck by President Okamura.
你好像还被冈村社长打了 对吗？
Who said that?
是谁说的？
Um, well…
这个…
He resented me because his business didn't work out.
那是因为他把生意失败怪罪到我头上
First of all, that was Isobe's client.
他明明是矶部负责的客户
Why is he holding a grudge against me?
怎么反而把气出在我身上呢？
Sorry.
抱歉
So the person in charge of Okamura Steel was someone named Isobe?
负责冈村钢铁公司融资的 是矶部先生吗？
I was the Section Chief of the Finance Department
正好那时候我是融资课课长
and Kaneda was previously in charge.
而金田是他们之前的负责人
It's not our fault.
我们两个都是代罪羔羊啊
Do you know which branch Mr. Isobe is working at now?
请问你知道矶部先生在哪间分行吗？
He could be attacked next.
他很可能会是下一个目标
I don't know.
我不知道
He was transferred somewhere because of Okamura Steel.
他因为冈村钢铁公司的事被调走了
Ask HR.
你们去问问人事部吧
His name is Mr. Takahiko Isobe.
他的名字是矶部隆彦
Yes.
是的
Do you know which branch…
是哪间分行？
He quit?
辞职了？
Two months ago… Yes…
两个月前吗？好的
Can you give me his contact number?
可以给我他的电话吗？
I am Soma from the Branch Inspection.
我是分行稽核班的相马
I am Hanasaki.
我是花琦
I am Isobe.
我是矶部
FORMER EMPLOYEE
（前职员 矶部隆彦）
I'm sorry for taking up your time.
特别叫你来一趟 真不好意思
It's okay.
没关系
I wanted to ask you about the incident regarding our employees
我们是想问问你有关我们的职员
who were attacked.
被袭击的事情
I read about it in the newspaper.
是 我在报纸上看到了
Mr. Mizuhara from the Kawasaki Branch
他们分别是川崎分行的水原经理
and Mr. Kaneda from Musashikosugi Branch. Do you know them?
以及武藏小杉分行的金田经理 你都认识吧？
I worked with them at the Toranomon Branch.
我在虎之门分行跟他们一起工作过
The police think that
警方怀疑
Okamura Steel has something to do with this case.
这次事件与冈村钢铁公司有关
You were in charge of that company, right?
这家公司当时是你负责的吧？
Yes.
是的
Would you tell us in detail about the company's bankruptcy?
请问你可以跟我们说说 那家公司破产的细节吗？
It's very simple.
原因很简单
The company couldn't receive the loan.
就是因为无法取得融资
Okamura Steel was performing badly at that time.
当时冈村钢铁公司的业绩在下滑
They applied for the additional loan.
社长就过来申请追加融资
Please! Tokyo Daiichi Bank is my last hope.
拜托了 东京第一银行是我最后的希望了
If you lend me 50 million yen, I can get back into shape.
如果你们能借我五千万 公司一定会好转的
Okay.
我明白了
Let me submit the application immediately.
我会马上提交申请书的
I worked hard on the proposal document because I wanted to help Mr. Okamura.
我很想帮助冈村社长 所以很努力地准备了书面申请
But by the time I took over the case from Kaneda,
可是我从金田那里 接手这件案子的时候
Okamura Steel was experiencing a significant drop in performance.
冈村钢铁公司的业绩就相当糟糕了
This company has been in the red for three years in a row.
写得太差了 他们已经连续三年财务赤字
They may go bankrupt if we don't offer them a loan this time.
如果我们这次不批准融资 他们很可能会破产
Did you think that you can get an approval with what you've presented here?
你觉得就凭你这份申请书 能获得批准吗？
Okay. I'll rewrite it.
我知道了 我再去重写一份
He ordered me to rewrite the proposal over and over again.
他命令我重写了一遍又一遍
No.
不行
RETURN
（退还）
Do it again.
重做
The loan isn't approved yet?
融资资金还是没有批下来吗？
The Chief hasn't approved it yet.
水原课长还没批准呢
Please give me some time.
请再给我一点时间
I have no time.
我没时间了！
My company will be finished if I can't get it
后天还得不到追加融资的话
by the day after tomorrow.
我们公司就完蛋了！
In the end, the settlement day came before the approval for the loan.
最后 到了结算日那天 融资依然没有被批准
Denied? Why?
否决？为什么？
Why?
为什么？
The Manager yelled at me for submitting this at the last moment.
这样急急忙忙地提交书面申请 经理可是骂了我一顿呢
But it was because of you…
可是 都是课长你…
Me? Is it my fault?
因为我？所以是我的错吗？
The time was up.
已经来不及了
President Okamura got very upset and came yelling at us.
冈村社长很生气 冲进来大闹了一场
This is all because of you.
都是因为你
Please stop it, Mr. Okamura.
请你住手 冈村社长！
-Shut up! -Mr. Okamura!
-闭嘴！ -冈村社长
That's terrible.
太过分了
You couldn't submit it in time
都是因为水原课长
because Section Chief Mizuhara made you rewrite it so many times.
一直要你重写书面申请 所以才来不及提交的吧？
No, it was because I wasn't good enough.
不是的 是因为我能力不足
I felt so sorry for President Okamura.
我对不起冈村社长
How is President Okamura doing?
冈村社长现在怎么样了？
The police are looking for him as a potential suspect.
警方认为他是嫌疑人 正在追查他呢
Mr. Isobe, you were also involved at that time.
矶部先生 你当时也牵涉其中
Please be careful.
请多加小心
I'll be okay.
我不会有事的
I have nothing to do with the bank now.
因为我跟银行已经没什么瓜葛了
RESTAURANT HANASAKI
（花琦居酒屋）
Do you think he's really the culprit?
这个人真的是犯人吗？
He does have a motive.
他确实有犯罪动机
But why do this now?
但为什么现在才报复呢？
I don't know. Maybe the opportunity arose.
不知道 或许是有什么契机吧？
If he had received the loan seven years ago,
如果七年前获得了融资
would the company have survived?
他的公司能得救吗？
No one knows the answer to that.
答案没人知道
Banks can make people happy,
银行可以使人幸福
but they make them unhappy too.
也可以使人不幸啊
But everything won't work out just because of a loan.
但得到贷款 也不表示解决了所有问题
Even if he had gotten it, he still could have failed.
就算他有资金了 也可能会撑不下去
Even if bankruptcy was postponed for a moment,
只是暂时延缓破产而已
it's hard to determine if that was best for the company.
这样对企业来说是不是好事呢？
I know, but…
我明白 可是…
But from the customer's point of view, they must think that
不 过 从客户的角度来看 他们一定会想
things would have been better if only the bank had approved the loan.
如果银行贷款批下来 事情就会好转了吧？
We're in trouble…
大事不好了…
That was delicious.
多谢款待
Today's daily lunch was very--
今天的午餐真是不错…
We're in trouble!
大事不好了
-I just had… -Have some tea. This is a new one.
-刚才… -喝口茶吧 这是新开的
The police called.
刚才警方打来了
They found the President of Okamura Steel.
说找到了冈村钢铁的社长
Where is he?
他在哪里？
He is in Shanghai.
在上海
Shanghai?
上海？
He started a business there and has not come back since then.
说在那里创业了 好几年没回来呢
Then…
也就是说…
He has an alibi.
他有不在场证明啊
President Okamura is not the culprit.
犯人不是冈村社长
Then who attacked Mr. Mizuhara?
那是谁袭击水原经理他们呢？
Branch Inspection.
喂？这里是分行稽核班
This is the front desk.
这里是接待处
Ms. Tagawa from the Toranomon Branch is here.
虎之门分行的田川女士来访了
What's the matter?
有什么事吗？
I couldn't tell you something yesterday.
其实 有一件事我昨天没告诉你们
What is it?
什么事？
It was about the man who was in charge of Okamura Steel.
是有关负责冈村钢铁的那位职员的事
-Mr. Isobe? -Do you know him?
-矶部先生吗？ -你们认识他啊？
We met and talked to him.
我们跟他见过面了
How is he doing? Was he okay?
他怎么样？还好吧？
I heard that he was really depressed.
我还听说他精神很颓废呢
He seemed to be a little tired.
他看上去的确有点疲惫
No wonder…
也难怪
Someone with a gentle heart is bound to get hurt in a place like a bank.
那么善良的人在银行这种地方待着 终究会受不了的
Were you close to Mr. Isobe?
你和矶部先生的关系很好吗？
Mr. Mizuhara didn't like us.
当时的水原课长不喜欢我们两个
So we complained together.
所以我们经常在一起发发牢骚
I heard that he was transferred because of Okamura Steel.
听说他是因为冈村钢铁的事被调走的
Is it true?
不是吗？
I am sorry.
对不起
Yesterday, I told you that I didn't know, but…
我昨天跟你们说不知道
Mr. Isobe is not the one who should be blamed.
但其实那不是矶部的责任
What do you mean?
什么意思？
It was bullying.
那是霸凌
Bullying?
霸凌？
Mr. Mizuhara was not planning to offer the loan from the beginning.
水原课长从一开始 就没想过要批准融资
Mr. Mizuhara was taking good care of Mr. Kaneda because he followed him,
那时金田是水原课长的跟班 就特别关照他
but he hated Mr. Isobe.
却很讨厌矶部
It was because Mr. Isobe opposed Mr. Mizuhara's way of doing things.
因为矶部总是反对水原课长的做法
Are you trying to say that I am wrong?
你是想说我错了吗？
Yes.
是的
As you know, he can't stand people who won't flatter him.
你们也知道的 他不喜欢不会讨好他的人
So he really got upset.
所以他真的很生气
Who do you think you are talking to?
你以为你在跟谁说话？
That's when Mr. Mizuhara started blatantly bullying him.
从那之后 水原课长就肆无忌惮地开始霸凌
How long have you been working in Finance?
你在融资课做多久了？
Ask the new employee how to write a proposal document.
去跟新人学学怎么写书面申请吧
Let's go out for drinks tonight.
好了 今天一起去喝酒吧！
Yes.
-好
You stay until you finish.
你做完了才可以回家
Let's go.
走吧
-Yes. -Where do you want to go?
-是 -你想去哪儿？
-How about Akasaka? -You like Akasaka.
-去课长喜欢的赤坂吧 -赤坂啊？
I can't believe it.
真不敢相信
Okamura Steel was the final straw.
致命一击是冈村钢铁公司的事
Mr. Mizuhara wanted to cut off Okamura Steel
冈村钢铁的业绩太不理想了
because it was performing badly.
水原课长就想终止融资
So he made Mr. Isobe take over Okamura Steel from Mr. Kaneda
所以他故意让矶部 从金田手上接过这个案子
and nitpicked his proposal document.
然后对他的书面申请挑三拣四
Do you really want to save this company?
你是真的想帮助这家公司吗？
Yes.
是的
Then what is this?
那这份申请是怎么回事？
Is it that bad?
有那么糟糕吗？
Please be more concrete…
请你具体地…
Use your brain to find that out.
你自己用脑子想想吧
Section Chief.
课长
Okamoto Steel definitely needs this loan.
冈村钢铁真的很需要这笔融资
If we're going to deny them, do it now
如果要拒绝的话 就应该马上通知
so that they have other options.
好让他们能申请其他金融机构
Shut up and rewrite it!
别说废话 重写
In the end, he couldn't submit the proposal document in time to get the loan,
结果 书面申请迟交了 融资无法批下来
and Okamura Steel went bankrupt.
冈村钢铁就破产了
Mr. Isobe took the responsibility and was transferred.
矶部必须此负责 于是被调走了
That's horrible.
太过分了
I agree.
是啊
He knew that Mr. Okamoto would be short of cash without the loan.
他明知道冈村社长 得不到融资的话就会资金短缺
This was all because he didn't like Mr. Isobe.
却因为讨厌矶部而做出这样的事
Mr. Isobe was excellent in the Finance Department, but he was
矶部本来是个优秀的融资课职员
pushed off the promotional ladder
却因此失去晋升的机会
and was transferred to many branches.
被各个分行调来调去
Um…
那个…
Do you think Mr. Isobe is the culprit behind this case?
你认为这次事件的犯人 是矶部先生吗？
If so, I want you to persuade him to turn himself in.
如果是他的话 我希望你们能劝他自首
Back then, everyone in the Finance Department including myself,
当年 我和其他融资课的同事们
wanted to save Mr. Isobe by any means.
都想尽办法帮助矶部
Although we knew the truth,
我们明明都知道真相
we couldn't say a word because we were afraid of Mr. Mizuhara.
却因为害怕水原课长而一声不吭
I have been regretting it all this time.
因此 我一直都无法释怀
I beg you…
拜托你们了
I understand.
知道了
I don't want to believe that Mr. Isobe did it.
我真的不希望是矶部先生干的
Maybe this is the reason why
矶部先生那天说自己不会有事
Mr. Isobe said that he'll be okay.
也许就是这个原因吧？
I'll be okay.
我不会有事的
Because he's the culprit.
因为他就是犯人啊
He's not answering.
没接电话呢
Yes.
喂？
Hello, Mr. Isobe?
喂？是矶部先生吗？
This is Soma from Tokyo Daiichi Bank.
我是东京第一银行的相马
I heard from Ms. Tagawa that you experienced a difficult time
我从田川小姐那里 听说你七年前在虎之门分行
at the Toranomon Branch seven years ago.
所遭受的不公正待遇
Please tell me.
请告诉我
Did you attack Mr. Mizuhara and Mr. Kaneda?
是不是你袭击了 水原经理和金田经理？
Mr. Isobe…
矶部先生
I worked for the bank for 20 years, but what was it all for?
我在银行工作了20年 到底有什么意义呢？
I wanted to start over in a new place
我从虎之门分行被调到其他分行时
when I was transferred to a local branch from Toranomon.
还想着要在新的地方重头开始
But I soon found out that I was naïve.
结果 我还是太天真了
Mr. Isobe, please.
矶部先生 拜托了
Wherever I went, there were rumors that I was
不管我去到哪 都有人谣传说
difficult to handle, because I had an X-mark on my career.
我是个难搞的家伙 那个污点一直跟随着我
I felt humiliated,
我觉得受到羞辱
but I tried to keep working to take care of my family.
但是为了家人 我还是撑下去了
However…
不过
I reached my limit.
我已经忍到极限了
I thought that I would be free from everything if I quit my job.
我以为只要辞职 就能无忧无虑了
My wife was worrying about my health,
我的妻子很担心我的身体
and I thought I did enough.
说辞了也好
But I was shocked after I left the company.
等到我辞职后 才大吃一惊
After I stopped wearing my suit and carrying my business cards,
我不穿西装、不拿着名片的话
I had nothing to prove that I once worked for a bank.
就没有任何在银行工作过的证明
I had nothing that could prove myself as a former banker.
我没有能够证明 自己曾是银行职员的东西
The moment I quit the bank, I lost everything.
离职的那一刻 我深切地体会到
I came to that realization.
我什么都没有了
That's when I happened to walk in front of the Kawasaki Branch.
就在那时 我恰巧路过川崎分行
Let me carry your bag.
我帮你拿公事包吧
-Hurry up and get a taxi. -Yes.
-小笠原 快点拦车 -是
-Where are you going tonight? -Akasaka.
-你要去哪里？ -赤坂吗？
I couldn't forgive him.
我无法原谅他
He didn't get hurt at all.
那个人无论到哪里都安然无恙
At that moment,
那一刻 我就决定了
I decided to remind them of what they'd done to ruin my life.
我要提醒他们对我的人生带来的苦难
I would take my revenge…
我决定对那些 让我当代罪羔羊的家伙们…
Who is it?
是谁？
…on those who made me a scapegoat.
…报复
Mr. Isobe.
矶部先生
Please turn yourself in.
请你去自首吧
You are not an employee of the Tokyo Daiichi Bank.
你已经不是东京第一银行的职员了
You are free.
你已经自由了
You don't have to deal with the humiliation from the past.
你没必要再忍受过去的屈辱
Please think of the future,
为了你的家人
for the sake of your family.
想想你们的将来吧
I am not done yet.
还没结束呢
Mr. Isobe.
矶部先生
There is one more person that I can't forgive.
还有一个我无法原谅的人
Someone who knew everything but turned a blind eye.
那个明明什么都知道 却视而不见的家伙
Who is it?
是谁？
Hello?
喂？
Who is the person that turned a blind eye?
那个视而不见的家伙到底是谁呢？
Mr. Mizuhara's boss… So the Branch Manager?
水原的上司是分行经理吗？
Who was it?
当时的分行经理是谁？
Let me check.
稍等
TORANOMON BRANCH
（虎之门分行）
BRANCH MANAGER TSUYOSHI SHINDO
（分行经理真藤毅）
Executive Director Shindo.
真藤常务
It was Executive Director Shindo.
是真藤常务
Mr. Soma…
相马
Let's go.
走
Yes.
请进
Excuse me.
打扰了
It's time for the finance committee meeting.
常务 是时候去金融座谈会了
Okay.
好
Mr. Shindo.
真藤先生
Who is it?
你是谁啊？
It was you.
是你
Let me go.
放开我
Stop it, Mr. Isobe!
矶部先生 请你住手！
Let me go!
放开我！
Mr. Isobe.
矶部先生
Please stop it.
住手吧！
Are you all right?
没事吧？
Stupid man.
愚蠢的男人
Come on.
好了
BRANCH INSPECTION
（分行稽核班）
How was it?
怎么样了？
He is being questioned at the police station.
他还在警局被问话
So everything is solved now?
所以事情算是解决了吗？
I guess so.
应该是吧？
What Mr. Isobe has done is not acceptable.
矶部先生做的事是不能被原谅的
But I think the one that drives an innocent person
但促使那么无辜的人犯罪的人
into committing a crime, is guilty of a more serious offense.
才真的罪恶深重吧？
Mr. Isobe said that
矶部先生说过
Mr. Mizuhara and the rest had ruined his life.
是水原经理他们毁了他的人生
What kind of place is a bank, where those people get promoted?
让那样的人晋升 银行到底算是什么地方啊？
You are right.
你说得对
Can't we do anything?
我们什么都做不了吗？
We are not the police.
我们不是警察
But…
可是…
But there are things that only we can do.
可是 有些事只有我们能做到
Come on. Let's go.
好了 走吧
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK TORANOMON BRANCH
（东京第一银行虎之门分行）
All right… Yes?
好了 请进
Excuse me.
打扰了
Nice to see you again.
又见面了
What happened?
怎么了吗？
I want to ask you for a favor.
我们想请你帮忙
Here it is.
是这里
TORANOMON BRANCH FINANCE DOCUMENT
（虎之门分行融资资料）
TOKYO DAIICHI BANK
（东京第一银行）
You're up and about now?
已经可以出院了吗？
I can't take any more time off just because of this.
可不能因为这点小伤一直休息啊
I can't rely on the Deputy Manager either.
而且副理也靠不住
If he does a poor job, I will have to be responsible.
要是他有什么做不好 负责任的可是我啊
But I can't believe I had to experience that.
不过我真没想到会发生这种事
I heard that you did too.
常务 你也被骚扰了吧？
Yeah.
是啊
HR should be blamed for keeping that
一直让那种罪犯待在我们的银行
criminal at our bank all this time.
人事部应该要负责啊
I want him to stay in prison for several years.
必须把他关进牢里几年才行
Yes.
请进
Excuse me.
打扰了
You two again?
又是你们两位啊
Do you need anything?
有什么事吗？
-I heard that Mr. Mizuhara is here. -What?
-我们听说水原经理来这里了 -什么？
Mr. Shindo should hear this too.
我们也想请问一下真藤常务
You're being rude. Please leave.
你们真失礼啊 出去吧
Yes. This is not a place for you to visit.
对 这里可不是你们能来的地方
I'll listen.
说吧
This case goes all the way to the Toranomon Branch seven years ago.
这是七年前发生在虎之门分行的事
Mr. Mizuhara,
水原经理
you delayed Okamura Steel's loan application on purpose, right?
你当时故意延迟提交 冈村钢铁公司的融资申请 对吧？
What?
什么？
Please answer me.
请你回答
I don't know. Why would I do such a thing?
我不知道 我为什么要干那种事啊？
It was to demean Mr. Isobe, who was in charge of it.
为了中伤身为负责人的矶部先生
You disliked Mr. Isobe because he had opposed you.
你很讨厌顶撞你的矶部先生
Okamura Steel's
于是
performance was declining, so you put Mr. Isobe in charge of it, and made it
你就让他负责 业绩正在下滑的冈村钢铁
go bankrupt.
再迫使该公司破产
I didn't do that.
我没干过那种事
Just as you planned,
正如你所盘算的
Mr. Isobe took responsibility and was transferred.
矶部先生需要为此负责 被调走了
Give me a break! You made up everything.
开什么玩笑？简直是胡说八道
You have no evidence of that.
你门根本就没有证据
I have evidence here.
证据在这里
These are the proposal documents you ordered Mr. Isobe to rewrite.
这是你当时让矶部先生重写的 追加融资书面申请书
Why do you have those?
你们怎么会有那种东西？
I found it.
找到了！
They were in the storage room at the Toranomon branch.
我们在虎之门分行的仓库找到的
We were able to find it because Mr. Shindo,
我们能找到这些资料 也要多亏当时的分行经理
the Branch Manager at that time, was very strict with managing documents.
也就是真藤常务 十分谨慎地把这些资料保存起来了
From July 21st to August 28th, Mr. Isobe rewrote the documents
从7月21号到8月27号这段期间 矶部先生重写的次数
a total of 17 times.
一共有17次
The 17th document was submitted two days before the settlement day.
而第17次重写的申请书 在结算日的两天前就被提交了
"A loan denial should be determined quickly."
“决定拒绝的融资应尽早做出决断”
That is the rule regarding loans.
这是融资界的规则
Mr. Mizuhara.
水原经理
What you did was clearly against the principle of faith and trust.
你所做的事很明显 违反了诚实守信的原则
Executive Director Shindo. Please believe me.
真藤常务 请你相信我
I never did such a thing.
我绝对没有干那种事！
I can't submit an application that's brought in at the last minute.
这样急急忙忙提交的申请书 怎么能通过呢？
Aren't you training your men?
你是怎么指导部下的啊？
I am sorry.
非常抱歉
I told Isobe so many times. He is such a problem.
我跟矶部说过好多次了 他真的很麻烦
I won't approve this.
业绩在下滑呢
Is this company okay?
这种公司没问题吗？
This company is performing poorly.
这家公司原本业绩就不好
We can't help it.
这也没办法呢
Anyway, this is all Isobe's doing.
总之这全是矶部的责任
I will make him take responsibility.
我会让他好好负责的
What are you guys trying to do?
你们到底想干嘛？
Listen, I am a victim.
听好了 我可是受害者
Isobe committed a crime.
矶部才是那个犯人
Are you going to overlook what he did to Kaneda and me?
难道那家伙对我和金田的袭击 可以不当一回事吗？
With all due respect…
请恕我直言
what Mr. Isobe did is not acceptable.
矶部先生确实犯下不可原谅的罪
But you're the one who made him into a criminal.
可是让矶部先生变成犯人的就是你
Shut up. What do you know about me?
闭嘴 你懂什么？
I don't know.
我不懂
I don't understand someone who demeans their subordinates just to
我不懂怎么会有人为了愚蠢的自尊心
protect his stupid pride.
而中伤自己的部下
What?
什么？
What you have done may not be against the law.
或许你的所作所为并没有触犯法律
There is no record
即使你霸凌矶部先生
of you bullying Mr. Isobe or kicking him out of the branch, and it won't
将他赶出分行 也不会留下记录
mark your career, either.
或在你的职业生涯上留下污点
In fact, you didn't even realize that you had incurred such hatred.
你甚至没有意识到 自己已经让对方心生怨恨
It is wrong for the life of a man with a family and future to be ruined by
但是像你这样 破坏一个有家庭、有未来的人的人生
a man like you.
那一定是错的
-Shut up! -No, I won't!
-住嘴！ -我不要！
You used dirty tricks and cornered your subordinate.
你利用卑鄙的手段将部下逼入窘境
Even worse, you let a company go bankrupt.
更糟的是 你还迫使一家公司破产
The position you got by doing that holds no worth!
靠这些手段得来的地位 一点价值也没有！
Mr. Mizuhara, we've already reported everything to HR.
水原经理 这次的事件 我们已经上报人事部了
HR said they will interview all related parties to investigate this.
他们说会对当时的相关人士 进行审讯调查
I'm sure they will be calling you too.
我相信他们也会跟你联系的
Mr. Shindo, help me.
真藤常务 请帮帮我
Please… Executive Director Shindo!
拜托了 真藤常务
Executive Director Shindo. May I ask you a question?
真藤常务 我可以问你一个问题吗？
Yes.
什么问题？
You were the Toranomon Branch Manager at the time.
你当时是虎之门分行的经理
Did you really think that
你真的认为
Mr. Isobe was responsible for Okamura Steel's bankruptcy?
矶部先生应该为冈村钢铁的破产 负上全责吗？
Or did you turn a blind eye knowing that it was planned
还是说你早就知道 这是水原经理一手策划的
by Mr. Mizuhara?
却选择视而不见呢？
Ms. Hanasaki, restrain yourself.
花琦小姐 你说话小心点
That was an important time for you as a Branch Manager.
当时是你 身为分行经理的重要时期吧？
If there was a rumor about bullying at your branch,
如果自己管辖的分行传出霸凌丑闻
your career would suffer.
你就没有晋升的机会了
That's why…
于是…
I don't have to answer that.
我没必要回答你这个问题
But I can say one thing.
我只想说一件事
In order to protect and promote the bank as an organization,
为了守护银行这个组织 使其正常运作
I can't help everybody.
光靠正义感是不够的
Even if it ruins the life of a person?
所以毁了别人的人生也无所谓吗？
If you didn't overlook what Mr. Mizuhara did,
如果当时你对水原经理的行为 采取行动的话
don't you think that Mr. Isobe would still be working here?
如今矶部先生 应该还在这家银行工作吧？
Maybe this sad case
这起可悲的事件
wouldn't have occurred.
也就不会发生了吧？
I have been trying to maintain
我一直以来
the honor of the Tokyo Daiichi Bank at all times.
都是以守护东京第一银行的名誉 作为优先考量
I have avoided hurting the name of our bank by all means.
无论采取什么措施 都要避免损害银行的声誉
That's all.
仅仅如此
Excuse me.
我先失陪了
A FEW DAYS LATER
（数日后）
Did they reach a settlement?
以和解告终吗？
Both Mr. Mizuhara and Mr. Kaneda dropped their charges.
水原经理和金田经理都撤销了控告
Making a big deal out of this
把事情闹得太大的话
will hurt the reputation of the bank.
会影响银行的名声
The media died down too, so it's all done.
媒体也平静下来了 所以事情就算解决了
Today's inspection is the Ueno Branch.
今天要稽核的是上野分行
Four administrative mistakes. Good luck.
四件行政失误 拜托你们了
Okay.
好的
I can't be happy about the way this ended.
对于这样的结果 总觉得高兴不起来呢
It seems that everything was done to protect the reputation of the bank.
这样的解决方式 都是为了保住银行的声誉吧？
Maybe.
应该吧？
But that turned out to be favorable for Mr. Isobe.
但对矶部先生来说也是件好事吧？
I know, but…
话是这么说
Kodama.
儿玉
I wanted to inform you about this.
我是来通知你们的
Mr. Mizuhara was demoted
水原已经受到了降职处分
and got dispatched to an affiliate company.
被调遣到子公司了
Mr. Kaneda will receive an official warning for having a part in
金田也因为袒护水原的不正当行为
Mr. Mizuhara's misconduct.
而受到了警告处分
I see.
是吗？
I don't care what you think,
不管你们怎么想
but let me tell you one thing.
我只是想告诉你们
It was Executive Director Shindo
说服那两个人
who persuaded them to drop the charges.
撤销控告的人是真藤常务
He introduced Isobe to an attorney he knows.
他给矶部介绍了熟识的律师
It is not only to protect the name of our bank.
不只是为了银行的名声
But he is also thinking about Isobe's future.
也是考虑到矶部今后的人生
He is that kind of a person.
他就是这样的人
That's all.
我说完了
Do you think that's true?
你觉得是真的吗？
I don't know.
不知道呢
But it's not bad to believe in him sometimes.
但偶尔试着相信他一下也无妨啊
Yes.
是
Cheers!
-干杯
Ms. Tagawa, thank you very much for your cooperation.
田川小姐 这次真的谢谢你的帮忙
-Thank you. -No, I want to thank you instead.
-谢谢 -说什么呢？是我谢谢你们才是
Mr. Isobe called to thank me today.
矶部今天打电话给我致谢
Now I can finally let go of my guilt.
我终于可以放下我的愧疚感了
-That's good. -Yes.
-那就太好了 -是啊
This is delicious.
这个很好吃耶
Master, this carpaccio is wonderful.
师父 这个生牛肉片太好吃了
-Master? -Really? Thank you.
-师父？ -是吗？谢谢你的夸奖
The flounder is a little salty, so it goes well with cold sake.
这道盐渍的比目鱼搭配冷酒也好棒啊
Can you tell?
你吃得出来吗？
This also goes well with Kabosu or wasabi soy sauce.
这个搭配柑橘或芥末酱汁也不错哦
Really? Will you give me the recipe?
真的吗？你可以把食谱告诉我吗？
Sure. Please come this way.
当然了 请过来这边
A man who can whip up these dishes is so cool.
能迅速做出这种菜的男人真不错啊
I am happy.
我好开心啊
Hey, they look good together.
喂…这气氛不错嘛
Right.
是啊
Is it that lucky charm you gave him?
是不是你送的护身符灵验了？
The love charm!
保佑恋爱顺利
I bought the same one too!
可是我也买了一个啊
You said you didn't need any lucky charm.
你不是说不需要什么护身符的吗？
It might work for me too.
说不定我的也会灵验呢
Ten million?
-一千万？
We'll be in big trouble if we can't find it.
要是找不到那张本票 这可是个大失误
I don't know.
但是我真的没有印象
There must be a clue here.
线索就在现场
Time's up.
已经到期限了
-Mr. Hotta? -I will take responsibility.
-堀田先生？ -我会负责的
A banker's job is not that simple.
银行的业务不是那么简单的事
That's wrong.
这样是不对的